Haim Gamzu Collection of Israeli Theater
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Haim Gamzu Collection of Israeli Theater
1921-1958
GEN MSS 1426
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.8
6 boxes + 1 broadside
The Haim Gamzu Collection of Israeli Theater includes production programs, newspaper clippings and other printed material; production photographs; and posters. The material documents the development of theatrical production in Israel from the 1920s through the 1950s. Theaters represented include Habimah, Hamatateh, Ohel, Te'atron ha-Kameri shel Tel-Aviv, and others. Additional material includes photographs and printed material about Israeli actor Ari Kutai, and caricature drawings of prominent Israeli figures by Ze'ev.
Gamzu, Haim, 1910-1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Kedem Auctions, Ltd. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Haim Gamzu (1910-1982), was an Israeli art and drama critic. He was born in Chernigov, Russia, and went to Palestine with his parents in 1923. He studied art and philsophy at the Sorbonne and the University of Vienna. He became the director of the Tel Aviv Museum in 1962, and he established and taught at Israel's first theater school, Beit Zvi, in Ramat Gan. Gamzu authored several books on painting and sculpture, and his articles on painting, sculpture and theater were published in the daily Haaretz and elsewhere.
Scope and Contents
The Haim Gamzu Collection of Israeli Theater includes production programs, newspaper clippings and other printed material; production photographs; and posters. The material documents the development of theatrical production in Israel from the 1920s through the 1950s. Theaters represented include Habimah, Hamatateh, Ohel, Te'atron ha-Kameri shel Tel-Aviv, and others. Additional material includes photographs and printed material about Israeli actor Ari Kutai, and caricatures of prominent Israeli figures by Ze'ev.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Production programs and clippings, 1921-1957. II. Photographs, 1929-1958. III. Materials Relating to Ari Kutai, 1926-1955. IV. Posters and Caricatures, 1921-1954.
Theater -- Israel; Theater critics -- Israel; Caricatures; Photographs; Theatrical posters; Theater critics -- Israel -- 20th Century; Gamzu, Haim, 1910-1982; Kutai, Aari; Zeʼev; Habimah; HaMatateh; Ohel (Theater); HaTeatron Dramati; HaTeatron HaEretz-Israeli; Teʼaṭron ha-Ḳameri shel Tel-Aviv
- Production Programs and Clippings, 1921-1957; Series I; 0.42; 1 box
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of production programs and clippings dating from 1921 to 1957 and undated, regarding productions in theaters including Habimah, HaOhel, HaTeatron HaEretz-Israeli and Te'atron HaKameri. Also included are programs for performances of individual artists Deborah Bertonoff, Martha Graham, Yehudi Menuhin, and others.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by theater.
  - Habimah, 1922–1957 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - HaMatateh, 1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - HaOhel, 1926–1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - HaTeatron Dramati, 1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - HaTeatron HaEretz-Israeli, 1925-1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Hebrew National Opera, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Theater Zirah, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Te'atron ha-Kameri shel Tel-Aviv, 1945–1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Teatron Ivri, 1921–1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Various individual artists, 1949-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes Deborah Bertonoff, Martha Graham, and Yehudi Menuhin
  - Miscellaneous clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs, 1929-1958; Series II; 2.5; 3 boxes
  Arranged alphabetically by theater, then by title of production.
  Series II includes production photographs from theaters including Habimah ( The Dybbuk, The Glass Menagerie, Othello and others); HaMatateh ( From India to Ethiopia, The King of Lampedusa and others); HaOhel ( Bar Kochbah, For Whom the Bell Tolls, The Merry Wives of Windsor, and others); and Te'Atron ha-Kameri shel Tel-Aviv ( Anne Frank, As You Like It, The Miser, and others).
  - Habimah
    - Habimah theater exterior, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Anna Christie, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Black on White, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - The Blue Bird, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - The Caine Mutiny, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Casablan, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - The Castle, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - The Crucible, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Cry, the Beloved Country, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Death of a Salesman, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Desire Under the Elms, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Diary of Anne Frank, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - The Dybbuk, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - The Dybbuk, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 119)
    - Everyone Had Six Wings, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Fuenteovejuna, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - The Glass Menagerie, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Hannah Senesh, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Hedva and I, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - The Heiress, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - The House of Bernarda Alba, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - In the Wastes of the Negev, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - King Lear, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Living Dead, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Lysistrata, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Macbeth, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - A Man Cannot Be Understood, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Medea, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Medea, 1955 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 120)
    - The Miser, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Monserrat, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - The Most Cruel King, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Mother Courage and Her Children, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Night Storm, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - L'Oeuf, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Of Mice and Men, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Othello, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Pantomime with Marcel Marceau, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Peer Gynt, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Romeo and Juliet, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - The Servant of Two Masters, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - The Slaughter of the Innocents, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Snunit, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - The Street of Steps, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - A Tale of Three and Four, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - The Taming of the Shrew, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - The Teahouse of the August Moon, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Thieves' Carnival, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - A Touch of the Poet, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - The Visions of Simone Machard, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - The Wild Duck, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 66-72)
  - HaMatateh
    - From India to Ethiopia, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - The King of Lampedusa, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Woman of Valor, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - HaOhel
    - Alleys of Jerusalem, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Alleys of Jerusalem, 1941 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 121)
    - Bar Kochbah, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - The Black Saturday, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - The Blockade Breakers, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - The End of the World, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Everything's For the Best, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Une fille pour du vent, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - For Whom the Bell Tolls, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - The Good Soldier Schweik, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Guardians of the Walls, [1949] (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Hatching on the Rock, [1949] (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - The Herald, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Herod and Miriam, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Hershel of Ostropol, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - The Imaginary Invalid, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - The Inn, undated (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Jeremiah, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - King Solomon and the Cobbler, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - The Merry Wives of Windsor, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Prisoner No. 72, undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - The Respectful Prostitute, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Shulamit, undated (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - This City, undated (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - The Travels of Benjamin the Third, undated (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - The Wooden Dish, undated (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 102-103)
    - Envelope related to HaOhel photographs, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Te'Atron ha-Kameri shel Tel-Aviv
    - Anne Frank, undated (Box 3, Folder 105)
      Photograph of cast members with author Georges Duhamel.
    - As You Like It, undated (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - [ Les Contes de Lod ?], undated (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Gardens, 1949 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 122)
    - Good Woman of Setzuan, undated (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - He Walked Through the Fields, 1948 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 123)
    - Joan of Arc, 1952 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 124)
    - Look Homeward, Angel, undated (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - The Miser, undated (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Pygmalion, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Read Me Siomka, 1950 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 125)
    - Shadow, 1949 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 126)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 127)
- Material Relating to Ari Kutai, 1926-1955; Series III; 0.20; 1 box
  Arranged by type of material.
  Series III includes photographs, illustrations, and newspaper clippings relating to the actor Ari Kutai.
  - Portrait and candid photographs, 1938-1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Production photographs, 1927-1955, undated (Box 4, Folder 113-115)
  - Illustrations, undated (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Clippings, 1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 117)
- Posters and Caricatures, 1921-1954; Series IV; 1.7; 1 box + 1 broadside
  Series IV includes two posters from HaTeatron Haivri and HaTeatron HaEretz-Israeli, both from 1921, and caricatures by Ze'ev of actors including Yitzhak Shiloh and other public figures.
  - Posters from HaTeatron Haivri and HaTeatron HaEretz-Israeli, 1921 (Box 5 (Broadside))
  - Caricatures of actors and other public figures by Ze'ev, 1954, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 118)